Welcome to this prep lecture on
Balanced Ligamentous Tension.
This technique is a
very powerful technique,
yet gentle and is
widely applicable
to various regions of the body.
In addition to watching
this lecture, please also
watch the separate BLT
lecture on this topic.
In addition, complete
the CPG assignments
and self-assessment questions.
Also watch the required
OMM lab videos.
Here are today's session
objectives. As stated
on this slide, there
are also review
topics for both diagnosis
and treatment, and we
do this to again
encourage you to continue
to revisit, relearn,
refine your technique
so that you don't
forget about it, and
of course to help
prepare you for exams.
This material is testable on
both written and
practical exams.
More importantly,
in practice, patients often
benefit from having multiple
techniques done, or at
least it's useful for you as
a future provider to be
able to perform various
techniques, knowing when and
how to perform each one, and
their effects can often be
complementary and provide.
the necessary benefit that you
hope to gain from
doing techniques.
So again, the practical reason,
meaning in clinical
practice, is that
the more tools you
have, the more options
you have to help
people when needed.
Here we have the principles
and basic steps of
balanced ligamentous
tension. If you read the
definition at the top,
the minimalization of
periarticular tissue load
and the placement of the
affected ligaments in a
position of equal tension in
all appropriate planes so
that the body's inherent
forces can resolve the
somatic dysfunction.
If you look at this
definition, there
are a number of things
to keep in mind.
First is that we are
working three-dimensionally,
so it is important to
have an understanding
in both your mind and
your hands the three
-dimensional nature of many
somatic dysfunctions. For
example, in the spine,
the cervical, thoracic,
and lumbar spine, we often
talk about the flexion,
extension, side bending,
and rotation planes.
So while one does not
always have to work with
all three planes, at
the end of the day, the
body is a three
-dimensional structure. and
it's important to realize
that we have to take
multiple directions into
consideration often.
Also, by doing so we are
aiding the body to resolve
the dysfunction. So
we are not fixing the
dysfunction just on our
own. We are setting up the
directions in such a
way that there is this
minimalization of the load
around a joint in the tissues
around the joint and
thereby allowing the body to
hopefully correct or
at least improve that
dysfunction and this
improvement happens using these
three basic steps it can
be more involved than this
in terms of additional
terminology and this is
where hopefully you have
had a chance or will be
shortly reviewing the
longer lecture on BLT. The
basic steps are to disengage
so that you can first
allow some wiggle room,
this so-called free play
between the components
of structures that form
a joint or segment, such
as a vertebral segment.
So again, you just have
to think of it in those
logical terms. Before
you work for something,
it's useful to have a little
wiggle room and that's
what the disengagement step
does. And then the exaggeration
is to move the dysfunction
into its dysfunctional
pattern. Since somatic
dysfunction is conventionally
named in its directions
of ease, then exaggeration
means moving it into the
directions of freedom until
you feel a point of balance,
which is the final step.
It's important also to
recognize that balance is both
a concept you keep in your
mind but also something it's
tactile so i would say that
you can't fully understand
blt until unless you begin
to recognize how it feels
having said that it's subtle
or it can be subtle and
it can be difficult and
release may not always feel
the same even in the same
person for the same type of
dysfunction so give yourself
some wiggle room some and
some slack so to speak to
learn this material don't
get frustrated it's more
important that you understand
the concepts and then be
patient let your hands feel
what they feel and keep in
mind that any releases that
you feel may also take a while
or sometimes they actually
can happen more quickly
than you might realize and
there can also be multiple
releases so again the
key is to work with work
with these concepts try to
get in your hands BLT
can be performed directly
also but most often it is
indirect so if you hear the
term BLT, you can most
likely assume that it is
indirect. I don't want to
speak for all instances.
But for our purposes,
BLT is indirect,
unless we are
asking specifically
for the direct component.
The following just provides
some additional details.
This is applicable really
to many OMM techniques.
In terms of forces,
it's already
noted BLT is
typically indirect.
And if you think about
it, the importance of
localization is to make
sure that you are working on
the area that you are
aiming to work on, but
also once you're there
most of the work has been
done already in terms of
being in that region. So
typically your amplitude,
your forces are going to
be relatively small because
you're already in the zone.
If you are in that zone
of influence for that
somatic dysfunction then you
really don't have to do too
much distance or force
wise to get that particular
dysfunction to to balance
back to the balance part
by balancing we require
constant feedback so that we
can adjust our forces, our
direction, or directions.
And if you think of everyday
example of trying to
balance an object, you will
understand what I mean.
That means that for
BLT, we are constantly
trying to pay attention.
Again, this is true for
other techniques also,
but in BLT especially,
this is particularly
important because how
else will one one find
this point of balance so
it takes patience it
takes awareness it takes
a loop of faith at least at
the beginning but trust in
the process and it will pay
off in terms of enhancing
your preparatory skills and
follow the principles blt
although categorized as
passive can involve some
patient involvement and whether
a blt technique describes
it or not often one can
involve respiratory cooperation
as long as the patient is
able to cooperate. So one
example that's described
in the handout in terms of
respiratory influence is to
have the patient breathe in
and breathe out and see
which direction relaxes the
tissues more at the dysfunctional
segment. If you can't
decide, then choose one or
the other. And if neither
makes a difference, you can
leave this out. But officially
speaking, we're going
to hold you to what's
described in the handout, but
recognize that in practice,
respiratory cooperation is
something that you can use
that may that may help you
further get that release as
with any OMT reassess with
BLT again you're constantly
reassessing to find a
balance point so that you can
then allow the the body to
through its inherent forces
to relax the tissues and
feel those releases so
the balance point is not the
same thing as the release
point balance taking
things into this state of
balance is what then allows
the inherent forces to
work to allow you to get
the release so please keep
that in mind so we treat
an area we reassess it and
often this just This means
relaxing your hand contact,
relaxing your mind for
a moment, and then going
right back to it and testing
the somatic dysfunction.
An everyday example would
be like if you're looking
at the TV screen or computer
screen for a long time,
your senses kind
of get accustomed
to it and they can get dull.
So looking away and even
for a few seconds and
going back to it gives
you a fresh perspective.
and that's what
reassessment does. It allows
you to disengage from
intellectually and
manually for even a
moment, and that will
give you added clarity
when you reassess it.
The VLT techniques you
will learn in this lab
will be for the cervical,
spine, thoracic spine,
the lumbosacral spine, as
well as for the fibula.
So please review the
mechanics of the fibula. keep
in mind that even though
we reference the fibular
head for diagnosing,
it is really the entire
fibular that we want to
pay attention to, both with
our hands and with our
mind, as we try to visualize
the anatomy and adjust
our forces accordingly.
Keep in mind also that a
component of the fibular
technique includes addressing
the intraosseous membrane.
As you learn BLT, I hope
you approach it with
curiosity and wonder. It is
a set of obstacles, but I
think there is an intuitive
aspect to it as long as
you have a firm enough
understanding of the basics.
If you take a look
at the child on the
left, twisting the
chains of a swing seat,
you can think of that as
rotation, for example, in
a direction of ease. But
if you go too far, it will
start to bind. So it has
to be more than just moving
the body part in a
particular direction. One has
to have the constant tactile
feedback to know when
enough is enough. And that's
a big part of this lab
is to not only learn the
basic steps so that you
can get in to the vicinity
of where you need to be
to allow the body to then
use the inherent forces to
release the dysfunctional
part that you were working
with but also to feel
in real time the process
of trying to get to this
balance point and once you're
there to feel any releases
that might arise out
of you taking the body to
that balance point. And
keep in mind there can be
multiple balance points
one after the other and
therefore multiple releases.
In this lab we have
two palpatory exercises
that will help guide your
sense of palpation so
that you can learn both
BLT and other techniques
such as cranial
osteopathy in future labs.
These are definitely
not the only exercises.
The key is to come in
with an open mind, relaxed
posture, making sure
that the table height
is good for both your
partner and you as the
student doctor, and being
patient in the process.
We will describe various
phenomena that you may be
able to feel and if you do
great if you don't don't
worry everyone learns at
their own pace and chances
are you are feeling what
you're supposed to but
just not recognizing it
so matching your palpatory
findings to an actual
understanding or recognition
that you are feeling
something and being able to
express it in words, that
is a process. And it's
perfectly okay for you
to just not be sure or be
able to sense just a
fraction of what we describe.
We would have this
exercise for both
the forearm and
lumbosacral spine.
For this and the
following slides on the
various techniques,
please have your hand out
available in case you
need to refer to it.
So let's talk about
BLT of the cervical
spine. I'll use
the example of C3
extended, rotated,
and side bent right.
C3ERS right for short.
As shown here, the patient
is supine. One makes two
contacts. One using a
finger on the articular
pillar of C3 on the left
side, which is not shown.
Again, a contact on the C3
left articular pillar, and
then a contact on the C4
right articular pillar.
So a contact on the left at C3,
a contact on the right at C4.
Why this opposite
contact? Because we will
be lifting these fingers
towards the ceiling.
That allows us to not
only get through the
paraspinal soft tissue
so that we can adequately
control these segments
and sense them but it
naturally extends the
cervical spine which works
out well in the in the
case of an extended
dysfunction it allows
us to easily apply more
extension by pushing by
lifting further or backing
off slightly if we don't
want to create as much
extension by having the
opposite contacts also when
we lift we create right
rotation of c3 relative
to C4. Since we don't want
C4 to move while we're
doing this, by having the
contact on the C4 right
articular pillar, this
prevents it from rotating
right also. Hence what I
mean by counterbalance.
So again, lifting creates right
rotation of C3 relative to C4.
It allows us to get through
the soft tissues and
to sense and control these
two vertebrae what about
side bending since it is
a ERS right dysfunction
we can control side
bending by translating both
contact fingers meaning
both C3 and C4 towards the
left by translating to the
left we create right side
bending let's talk about
two additional details
that are not described in
your handout if this were
a for a moment a flex
dysfunction instead of C3
ERS right if it is a C3
FRS right in that scenario
backing off how much we
lift may not be enough to
take it into the flexion
balance point in that case
we can actually lift the
head and upper neck slightly
enough for us to sense that
c3 is coming to a balance
point on c4 so that's for
flexion if one needs to
target a lower cervical
segment such as c6 or c7 one
would probably need to lift
the neck further flex the
neck further to target
those areas what about side
bending let's say your
fingers are not strong enough
or they are sore or the
neck is too tough for you to
translate adequately to
find a balance point in that
case you can in addition
to translation or perhaps
instead of translation you
can actually side bend the
neck to the level while
still monitoring the segment
so for c3 ers right one
could actually side bend the
neck to the right if you
are using both translation
and side bending then most
likely you will be using
not be using that much motion
of either in order because
you're combining them.
So that's a detail that I
wanted to share with you to
give you further options.
Here we have BLT of
the thoracic spine.
According to the Nicholas
Atlas, this is used for
T1 and T2 non-neutral
type 2 dysfunctions.
The example here is T1 flex
rotated side bent right.
Depending on the
length of your fingers
relative to the patient,
you can probably
use this for T3 and
even T4. But for testing
purposes, we'll limit
it to T1 and T2.
When we say T1 is FRS
right, we mean relative to
T2. And I mention this
because this technique has
you work with t2 and really
just fine-tune using t1
and I do not want this to
be a point of confusion
we start by making contact
as shown in picture a
over the transverse
processes of t1 and t2 for
t1 we use the index
fingers for t2 we use
the third fingers, meaning
the middle fingers.
Once we make these contacts,
we lift the fingers on
T2 transverse processes
or relax the lift to fine
-tune, excuse me, to tune
into the flexion extension
component. Because we're
monitoring both T1 and T2, it
is okay to be pushing
on the lower of the two
segments, meaning pushing on
T2 instead of T1, according
to the atlas. When we push
on T2, as long as we're
monitoring the motion, the
forces that are between T1
and T2, we can still tune
in to the balance point.
We then, still controlling
and monitoring T2,
we then side bend and
rotate T2 to the left.
This will be better
understood once you are in the
lab, especially for the
side bending component,
which is not too clear in
the picture. But again,
you have contacts on both
transverse processes of
T2. And by having this
bilateral contact, you will
be able to control for
the side bending and
rotation. So we side bend
left and rotate left at T2.
And what this does is it,
relatively speaking, T1
then rotates and side
bends right, which is
the somatic dysfunction.
Lastly, in D, we side
bend and rotate T1 to the
right to fine-tune, to
find the balance point. So
by going through steps B,
C, and D, we target the
flexion, then the rotation,
and the side bending.
The potentially confusing
point, as I already mentioned,
is that we're doing the
flexion extension and the
initial side bending rotation
through the contact on T2,
and it's not until the
last step according to the
technique as described in the
atlas to work on t1 itself
to sideband and rotate
it right next we have blt
of the thoracic spine this
is for t4 to t12 neutral
type 1 dysfunctions according
to the atlas use the
example is t8 neutral
sideband left rotated right
This could be the
middle curve of a middle
segment or the apical
segment of a group curve,
or it could be the
less common but
possible single segment
type 1 dysfunction.
But regardless, the
treatment is the same.
We start as shown
in picture A by
contacting the left
transverse process of T8.
Notice how the fingers
cross the patient's midline.
The patient then lies
supine while the physician
takes the opposing area
of the lower ribcage
matching the level of the
dysfunction in the back.
And in this instance,
the doctor pulls that
right lower ribcage
towards him to create right
translation, which
creates left side bending.
This is the direction
or one of the directions
of ease for this
patient's dysfunction. the
patient can facilitate
further side bending
also by lowering their
left shoulder lastly we
lift the finger that is
contacting the left transverse
process of T8 to induce
right rotation further
lifting of the finger meaning
pushing the left transverse
process anteriorly
further lifting creates
further right rotation so
the goal is to find that
balance point one can also
flex that same finger which
induces slight translation
of ta to the right which
in turn creates left side
bending so note how by
stacking all these different
vectors one accomplishes
taking the dysfunction
into its directions
of ease to find
the balance point
that hopefully
results in a release.
Now on to the third
and final BLT technique
for the thoracic spine,
also for T4 to T12,
neutral or also known
as type 1 dysfunctions.
As you already know, This
technique is performed
seated, however, unlike
the previous two.
The doctor stands behind the
patient's back. The example
here is T6, neutral side
bent right, rotated left.
One contacts the left T6
transverse process with
the left thumb and the T7
right transverse process
with the right thumb. One
then instructs the patient
to flex until one feels
T6 move on top of T7.
This way we know we are in
the vicinity of where we
want to be. Then we have
the patient slightly extend.
This allows us to
further localize to
the flexion extension
balance point.
One then has the patient
tilt or lower the right
shoulder enough to create
side bending and also
rotate the torso, the
upper body to the left.
So again, by having the
patient side bend to
the right and rotate
to the left, we follow
the directions of the
somatic dysfunction.
By having these
monitoring points,
we can monitor for
the balance point.
Note also that with this
technique as described,
it is not the action of
our thumbs that is allowing
the balancing to happen.
Our thumbs are there
as a little bit of a
stabilization effect
because they are
contacted contacting the
patient's back while
they are seated but
it is meant as a
sensing type of contact
and it is the patient's
rotation then done inside
bending that allows us
to find the balance point
In this example, we are
using the diagnosis of
L5, flex-rotated and
side-bent to the right,
hence the title BLT of
the lumbosacral spine.
The same principles can
be applied to other lumbar
levels. For example, if
it were a L4 dysfunction,
we would contact L4
and L5 with our hands.
But returning to this
example of L5 FRS right,
one hand contacts across
L5 and the other along the
sacrum. In this example,
the patient is supine.
We would move our
sacral hand cranially,
meaning cephalad, and
caudally relative to
L5 so that we can find
a point of balance.
Again, because it
is indirect, we
will go in a direction of ease.
With our other hand on
lumbar spine we would further
adjust by lifting it
meaning raising it towards
the ceiling this means
anterior with the patient
supine or we can lower
our hand meaning bring it
closer towards the table
but at all times we will we
will be maintaining the
contact on l5 and we pay
attention again to the
flexion and extension ease.
By lifting it, we would
induce extension. And by
lowering our hand, we
would ease up on extension.
And going back to
our sacral hand,
actually before we
do that, we can fine
-tune further at L5
using, as shown in D,
rotation and side
bending of L5 to
the right to match
the diagnosis.
Again, we understand
the diagnosis before we
proceed, but it's very
important for one to
really go by feel at this
point. So we take what
we know in our head,
but also follow our
palpatory sense. So in
this instance, performing
it indirectly, we will
go with the freedoms.
Keep in mind that we will
likely be moving both
hands, if not exactly at the
same time simultaneously,
in close sequence,
one after the other,
so that we can find
that balance point.
The motions will be subtle
and there'll be times
where you might not actually,
probably won't see any
motion, which is difficult
already, of course, because
your hands will be under
the patient in the lumbar
and sacral regions but
again your palpatory sense
as you get better and
better at this will
likely outmatch anything
that you will see
you find a balance
point and wait for the
release and once it is
completed you reassess
Here we have BLT of the
fibula. This technique
aims to not only address
the somatic dysfunction
at the fibular head,
whether it is an anterior
fibular head or the
more common scenario of
a posterior fibular head,
but this technique also
addresses interosseous
membrane dysfunction.
This membrane is located
between the fibula and
the tibia, and it spans
the length of the fibula.
So this technique
then really hinges
on the principle of
not just ligamentous
release but also
membranous release.
One should have a
proper contact at both
the fibular head as
well as the lateral
malleolus as shown in
the diagram on the left.
And again palpate firm
enough yet gentle enough
for it to be comfortable
but again secure enough so
that you are contacting
at the bony level. Any
movement that you feel
and perhaps see will be
minuscule because you are
addressing rather small
movements. So any large
movements should cue you into
the fact that you might
be sliding on the skin.
And as you do this technique
and you follow the description,
descriptions, the various
steps in the handout, keep
in mind that it can be a
little bit confusing. meaning
the fibula, because of the
seesaw motion, is not just
purely an anterior and
posterior motion because it
has a point of pivot and
keeping in mind the seesaw type
action, meaning at the fibula
head, for example, that
moves posteriorly, you
can feel and imagine your
mind's eye that the lateral
malleolus would move anteriorly.
So there is a fulcrum, so
to speak to this motion
so as a result of that if
you push anteriorly on the
lateral malleolus you can
imagine how it would also go
slightly superiorly and if
you push anteriorly at a
on a posterior aspect of
a posterior fibrillar head
diagnosis then it would shift
anteriorly but also slightly
superiorly. Now in the case
of an anterior fibrillar
head, you can debate whether
it would have the same
superior type motion
characteristics. But regardless,
ultimately this technique
hinges on the fact that you
have a concept in your mind
of what joint motion is,
as well as what you actually
feel. So ultimately you
start with how the handout
description shows and then
you follow the motion as
the way you perceive it.
And the whole point is to then,
once you take it into an
anterior motion, whether
direction at the lateral
malleolus or at the fibular
head, you also fine-tune
it by using a total motion,
meaning both hands moving
in the same direction,
either superiorly or
inferiorly, in order to address
the interosseous membrane
component and once you
have all of this balance
and you wait for the
release then you can reassess
your fibular head diagnosis
and you can even hold
the fibular heads same as
you would for the treatment
but then shift it in
an anterior posterior
direction as well as a and then
in a superior and inferior
direction in order to
see if you have better
sense of ease and evenness
to in motion in the different
directions of motion.
This concludes this lecture.
Thank you for your attention.